<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The falsehood of Mr. VVilliam Pryn's Truth triumphing, in the antiquity of popish princes and Parliaments. To which, he attributes a sole, sovereigne, legislative, coercive power in all matters of religion; discovered to be full of absurdities, contradictions, sacriledge, and to make more in favour of Rome and Antichrist, than all the bookes and pamphlets which were ever published, whether by papall or episcopall prelates, or parisites, since the reformation. With twelve queries, eight whereof visit Mr. Pryn the second time, because they could not be satisfied at the first.</title>
            <author>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1672</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E273_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E282_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200048</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860851</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860851</idno>
            <idno type="VID">158481</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91879)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158481)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 45:E273[16] or 47:E282[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The falsehood of Mr. VVilliam Pryn's Truth triumphing, in the antiquity of popish princes and Parliaments. To which, he attributes a sole, sovereigne, legislative, coercive power in all matters of religion; discovered to be full of absurdities, contradictions, sacriledge, and to make more in favour of Rome and Antichrist, than all the bookes and pamphlets which were ever published, whether by papall or episcopall prelates, or parisites, since the reformation. With twelve queries, eight whereof visit Mr. Pryn the second time, because they could not be satisfied at the first.</title>
                  <author>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed in London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Henry Robinson by Wing.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Prynne, William.  Truth triumphing over falshood (Wing P4115).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy E.273[16]: "This sheet was taken a printing munday ye 17th march 1644 .."; on copy E.282[11]: "May 8th";.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: item at reel 45:E.273[16] lacks all but quire C (p. 9-16).</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prynne, William, 1600-1669. --  Truth triumphing over falshood --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Puritans --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:158481:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE FALSEHOOD OF M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. VVILLIAM PRYN'S <hi>TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH TRI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MPHING,</hi> In the Antiquity of Popiſh Princes and PARLIAMENTS.</p>
            <p>TO WHICH, He attributes a <hi>Sole, Sovereigne, Legiſlative, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive power in all matters of Religion;</hi> diſcovered to be full of abſurdities, contradictions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſacriledge, and to make more in favour of <hi>Rome</hi> and Antichriſt, than all the bookes and pamphlets which were ever publiſhed, whether by Papall or Epiſcopall Prelates, or Pariſites, ſince the Reformation.</p>
            <p>WITH Twelve Queries, Eight whereof viſit Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> the ſecond time, becauſe they could not be ſatisfied at the firſt.</p>
            <p>Printed in <hi>London,</hi> 1645.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:158481:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:158481:2"/>
            <head>EPIST. DEDICATORY. <hi>To Mr.</hi> William Fryn <hi>of</hi> Lincolnes Inne, <hi>Eſquire.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> May ſafely appeale to Whatſoever is of eſteeme and deare unto you, how I could much rather have bemoan'd in private that perverſe and implacable ſpirit of yours, had not you of late ſo inconſiderately beſpatter'd ſo many Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, which have infected the very aire, far worſe than any moſt malignant e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidemicall contagion, by having inherited the priviledge to be cryed up and downe the ſtreets and publicke places, inſtead of Royall Proclamations, to the great ſcandall of your moſt conſcientious Brethren, and ſuppreſſing truth both Spirituall and Civill, which had more than begun to ſhine out ſo gloriouſly, ſince the firſt aſſembling of this preſent Parliament.</p>
            <p>You have done as much as in you lyes to divide the Independents from the Parliament, by grudging them a peaceable abiding place in the land of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; and provok'd our Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> by fixing or faſtning upon Chriſtian Emperours, Kings, Magiſtrates, Parliaments, the <hi>undoubted legiſlative coercive power in all matters of Religion,</hi> Title page; and that even without the aſſiſtance or advice of Synods; page 88. I doe but advertiſe you thereof, though it be knowne ſo publickly, that <hi>Aulicus</hi> tooke notice of it ſo long ſince: conſider the high conſequences thereof, and the miſchiefe it may grow unto, unleſſe prevented opportunely.</p>
            <p>Both King and Parliament pretend to have taken up Armes to defend the Proteſtant Religion, &amp;c. and yet fight one againſt another, no leſſe, than both of them oppoſed it: The King wonders the Parliament ſhould entertain Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts and Anabaptiſts to fight for the Proteſtant Religion; and the Parliament marvels no leſſe that the King ſhould entertaine Papiſts to doe the ſame: But may they not both alike wonder at each other in this particular? or rather, why ſhould either of them at all wonder at ſuch proceedings, ſince the Papiſts in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of doctrine beleeve all which Proteſtants beleeve; and both Browniſts and Anabaptiſts hate Popery and ſuperſtition as much as Proteſtants? But if the Proteſtant Religion can be truly propagated by fighting; ſurely both Papiſts, Browniſts and Anabaptiſts, even Turkes and very Dogs may be brought and taught to fight for it, all alike; but when you have ſpent your ſpirits, and diſtill'd away your braines, you will perceive at laſt if ever your eyes be open as I deſire unfainedly) that it is the moſt irrationall and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-Goſpel-like courſe under heaven, to imploy the arm of fleſh to work upon the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Take heed then what you ſay; or explaine to us what you and your party meane, when you make the ſupreme Civill Magiſtrate to be <hi>cuſtodem utri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tabulae:</hi> Tell us whether the <hi>Great Turke,</hi> Emperour, Kings of <hi>Spain,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:158481:3"/> 
               <hi>France, Poland, &amp;c.</hi> be not lawfull Civill Magiſtrates; how you can abridge them this Prerogative of both Tables, or quit their duty in taking charge of them, more than any Prince or Magiſtrate of Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>Did not <hi>Paul</hi> tell <hi>Timothy,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> in him, that <hi>the time would come when men would not indure ſound doctrine, but turne away their eares from the truth, heaping to themſelves teachers after their owne luſts,</hi> 2 Tim. 12 3, 4, 5. What if Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> were another <hi>Timothy,</hi> or had the very ſpirit of the ſelfe ſame <hi>Timothy,</hi> and could infallibly aſſure us that theſe were the times which <hi>Paul</hi> then ſpake of, and the Independents thoſe who were then foretold to have itching eares, and to be turned unto fables? may Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> be more officious, or exceed the commiſſion which was given unto <hi>Timothy,</hi> himſelfe? <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whoſe Apoſtle and Miniſter <hi>Paul</hi> was, gave <hi>Timothy</hi> no other, than that in ſuch a caſe he ſhould <hi>be watchfull in all things, indure afflictions, doe the worke of an Evangeliſt, make full proofe of his Miniſtery, reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all long-ſuffering and doctrine, v.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Conſider, I beſeech you, for the love of God and men, or your owne ſake, if you have any ſymtomes of reſpect to either; Does the Apoſtle, thinke you, there underſtand by reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all long-ſuffering and doctrine, that <hi>Timothy</hi> ſhould upbraid, reproach, defame ſuch as but differed from him in ſome opinion only, as you have done to Mr. <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> and that not for turning away from, but for holding out ſuch truths, as none in Scripture are more evident, or may more warrantably, and that more eaſily too, be made good, next to the very Scriptures themſelves to any equall judge, and even to every man himſelfe, who will not put out the eyes of his owne reaſon and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, to be led blindefold and ſuperſtitiouſly by other mens, whereof we can have no other aſſurance than what is full Popiſhly implicit? To doe the worke of an Evangeliſt, to make full proofe of his Miniſtery, is it, thinke you, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an informer of the Civill Magiſtrate? to provoke them unto wrath and rage againſt your Brethren of the Independent way? to become an accuſer of them, a perſecuter, a very executioner, (properties moſt eminently peculiar to the Arch-enemy both of God, and any thing like godlineſſe in any of his Saints) as you have done moſt tragically to your eternall infamy, unleſſe God in mercy worke your bitterneſſe of ſpirit into a more Chriſtian temper of mildneſſe and humility? which till attain'd to, ſhall continually be the prayer of One, who, till you be ſuch, or at leaſt, leſſe <hi>Baſilisk-like,</hi> muſt only reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your friend in private.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:158481:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Conceive it may not a little conduce towards the enlightning the Presbyterian party, to ſee the whole Catalogue of their errours, did they but once caſt an eye upon the fierce claſhings and diametricall contradictions, in which their moſt eminent Champions would incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderately involve them: to which purpoſe, amongſt many, I doe here in the two next pages preſent thee with ſome few of them as in a looking-glaſſe; peruſe them impartially, and when thou findeſt that no diſtinctions, how ſophiſticall ſoever, can poſſibly reconcile ſuch contrarieties, be jealous and ſuſpect the reſt; free thy conſcience from the thraldome and bondage of theſe Egyptian Spirituall Taske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters; diſclaime the very countenancing ſuch ſpirits, who care not what traſh and trumperies they vent, ſo they may gaine Proſelites and Contributions: Let Reaſon be thy guide, Peace and Truth thy aime; and the God of Peace and Truth, who requires no other than a reaſonable ſervice, will infallibly be both thy rewarder and reward it ſelfe: Farewell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:158481:4"/>
            <head>Divines of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> Diſcipl. <hi>pag. 89.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Nationall Aſſemblies ought alwayes to be received in their owne liberty, and have their owne place.—And all men, as well Magiſtrates as inferiours, to be ſubject to the judgement of the ſame in Eccleſiaſticall cauſes without any reclamation or appellation to any judge, Civill or Eccleſiaſticall within the Realme.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Doctor <hi>Adam Stuart's</hi> ſecond part of his Duply to the two Brethren, <hi>p. 30.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The Civill Magiſtrate is ſubject in a <hi>ſpirituall</hi> way unto the Church; He <hi>muſt</hi> learne Gods will by the Miniſters of the Church, who are Gods Ambaſſadours ſent to him; He <hi>muſt</hi> be ſubject to Eccleſiaſticall cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Mr. <hi>William Pryn</hi> in the Title page termes his Truth triumphing over Falſhood.</head>
            <p>A juſt and ſeaſonable vindication of the undoubted Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction, Right, Legiſlative, Coercive power of Chriſtian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Kings, Magiſtrates, Parliaments in <hi>all matters</hi> of Religion, Church-government, Diſcipline, Ceremonies, Manners.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Authour of the Pamphlet, entituled, <hi>The readineſſe of the Scots advance into England, 6. of November, 1643.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The Generall Aſſembly is ſubordinate to no Civill judicature what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>
               <hi>Apollonius</hi> Conſiderat. Quarund. Controverſ. &amp;c. p. 108.</head>
            <p>Particular Churches as well as Generall Aſſemblies have their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity immediately from God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Mr. <hi>Thomas Edwards</hi> ſayes in his Antapologia, <hi>p. 163.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Junius, Zanchius, Ameſius, &amp;c.</hi> make the ſubject matter of politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call adminſtration to be <hi>res humanae,</hi> humane things and matters; but of Eccleſiaſticall, divine and ſacred.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:158481:4"/>
            <p> Page 166. Is it that you doe give a power to the Magiſtrate in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall things, of the <hi>ultimate determination</hi> of matters purely Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, which the Presbyterians principles doe not, as in matters of doctrine ſcandall &amp;c. And page 168. Spirituall remedies and meanes muſt be uſed in the Kingdome of Chriſt, and by them Chriſt doth his worke. And hence in Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline, and thoſe ſcandalls in the Church, which are the point in hand; puniſhments in the body or in the purſe, which can be by the power of the Magiſtrate, have no place.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Divines of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> in a booke called, A Diſpute againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Popiſh Ceremonies obtruded upon the Church of <hi>Scotland, p. 150.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>It followeth that Chriſt hath committed the power of judging, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining, and making lawes about thoſe matters, <hi>viz.</hi> which concern the worſhip of God, not to Magiſtrates, but to the Miniſters of the Church.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Calvin <hi>Inſtitut.</hi> l. 4. c. 11. ſect. 16.</head>
            <p>Since the Church hath of its owne any power of compelling, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may require it (I ſpeake of Civill coercive power) it is the duty of pious Kings and Princes to uphold Religion by their lawes, edicts and judgements.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Junius <hi>Controverſ.</hi> 3. l. 3. c. 26. ſect. 12.</head>
            <p>Whereas ſome things are matters of conſcience, and belong to the judicatory of Heaven (that I may ſpeake according to the Canoniſts;) others humane and temporall appertaining to an earthly judicatorie; in ſacred, divine, and Church affaires, the judgement is never lawfully committed unto the Civill Magiſtrate, no, not to the Emperour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, becauſe holy things are of another Kingdome and cognizance.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:158481:5"/>
            <head>Six Impoſsibilities which doe neceſſarily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company perſecution for cauſe of Conſcience.</head>
            <p n="1">1 IT is impoſſible that the Goſpell ſhould come to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched unto all Nations, if men may be queſtioned for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of conſcience.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is impoſſible that ſuch as know but in part, ſhould grow in knowledge or from one meaſure and degree of faith unto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It is impoſſible that in a rationall way there ſhould be a firme ſecure peace throughout the world, nay not in a Province, City or Towne, ſo long as men make a point of conſcience to compell one another to their opinions.</p>
            <p n="4">4 It is impoſſible to preſcribe ſuch a way for ſuppreſſing new or different opinions whatſoever, which to any State or Church may ſeeme hereticall, but there will ſtill be left a gap, a poſſibility of fighting againſt God, even when ſuch State or Church thinke they fight for him moſt of all.</p>
            <p n="5">5 It is impoſſible that either the weake beleevers, miſ-beleevers or unbeleevers can be won by our godly converſation as is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 12. and 3. 1. 2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 12. 16. ſo long as we will not ſuffer them to live amongſt us.</p>
            <p n="6">6 It is impoſſible for a man to hold faſt the truth, or be fully perſwaded in his owne heart of what he does, of what Religion he makes choice of; unleſſe after he hath ſearched the Scriptures, and try'de the ſpirits whether they be of God or no, it be lawfull for him to reject that which ſhall appeare to him as evill, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to that which ſeems good in his owne judgement and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:158481:5"/>
            <head>The Falſhood of Mr. <hi>William Prynn's Truth Triumphing,</hi> briefly diſcovered.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur Title ſayes, <hi>Truth triumphing</hi> over <hi>Falſhood, Antiquity</hi> over <hi>Novelty;</hi> you meane, I ſuppoſe, <hi>Antick Truth</hi> over <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel Falſhood;</hi> And the truth is, whoever conſiders your enſuing Diſcourſe, will finde it to bee <hi>Antick Truth,</hi> very <hi>Antick;</hi> ſuch as to the Reformed World of Chriſtians would well neere have quite been antiquated, and totally become ridiculous, had not ſuch unskilfull Antiquaries as <hi>William Prynne</hi> of <hi>Lincolns Inn,</hi> Eſquire, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo much unneceſſary and thankles paines in gathering them up from Dunghills, and by whole Volumnes and Impreſſions to delude and cozen the unſtable people of his party; the truth whereof, that himſelfe and all others into whoſe hands this paper happens, may ſuddenly perceive; beſides the ſeverall abſurdities and contradictions, let them only take notice, that both the Truth and Antiquity hee ſo much ſpeakes and boaſts of, are deduced only from the abominable preſidents of ſuperſtitious Popery; ſome whereof I ſhall particularly, and yet briefly mention, as I finde them confuſedly peſtred amongſt themſelves, in the undigeſted rapſody of his more vaine Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>But before I leave the ſpecious Title thereof, I deſire all Readers may obſerve how amongſt others, you terme it a <hi>Vindication of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction Legiſlative of Chriſtian Emperours by Scripture texts;</hi> as if amongſt your Antick readings you had diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſome <hi>New-found-Land,</hi> wherein you would make your over cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous Diſciples thinke there had lived Chriſtian Emperours before, or at the writing of the Scriptures who verified your Antick Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Aſſertions.</p>
            <p>This Grand taske, like a very <hi>Atlas,</hi> you pretend to take upon you in Refutation of Mr. <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> without ſo much as diſturbing any of his arguments, or of the Anſwers to your twelve Queſtions, which, both your Epiſtle and the latter part of your Booke take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of; but becauſe you cannot make a ſatisfactory Reply, and yet are not ſo ingenuous as to acknowledge it and yeeld to Truth, you
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:158481:6"/> traduce as <hi>malicious</hi> and <hi>full of virulencie againſt Preſbytery and the Scots,</hi> page 125. and <hi>worſe then the Popiſh Gunpowder plot,</hi> Epiſt. Dedic. Are not theſe powerfull Arguments able to confute the very Apoſtles had they but been alledged in their dayes by ſuch an irreconcileable and implacable ſpirit as is Mr. <hi>Prynn's</hi> (witneſſe, beſides others, his proceedings againſt Colonell <hi>Fines?)</hi> Surely your friends will thinke you have better in your budget, or be aſhamed of you, when they have leiſure but to conſider of it.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, you complaine that Mr. <hi>Rutherfords due Rights of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery,</hi> Mr. <hi>Thomas Edwards</hi> his <hi>Anti-Apologia,</hi> and <hi>Gulielmus Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonius,</hi> with the <hi>Vallacrean</hi> Miniſters, were never anſwered.</p>
            <p>'Tis likely the Independents doe not deſire to make, no nor bee thought to have any difference with their <hi>Scotch</hi> Brethren, if poſſibly to be avoided; and you know the Proverb ſayes, <hi>The ſecond blow makes the fray;</hi> And though you would not take notice of a compleatly fit and full anſwer to Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> and ſo much the more, becauſe 'twas made by a milde, meeke ſpirited ſervant of God, quite contrary to that of Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> his; I hope Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> will no longer ſay Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> is not anſwered, now that Mr. <hi>Chidley</hi> hath ſo clearly and fairly foyld him the ſecond time; And that you may ſee <hi>Apollonius</hi> ſpeakes no better Latine for Presbytery than you doe Engliſh, pleaſe but to caſt your eye upon <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 44, 45. in anſwer to the Aſſemblies letters to the Churches of <hi>Zealand,</hi> where he ſayes in ſubſtance, <hi>That the body of Beleevers in generall have not a power of governing and judging Eccleſiaſticall matters by any ſpirituall juriſdiction; but that the Preſbyters themſelves have received this power of ruling immediately from Chriſt the King of the Church:</hi> which, what ever he alleadge to prove it with, theſe groſſe abſurdities, beſides how many others, will plainely follow:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That all Church Officers have either intruded themſelves into their offices, or elſe they muſt have beene thruſt in by ſome ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall meanes; of the latter there is no evidence; of the former there is no allowance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the Beleevers the Brethren did not chooſe the Officers, ſo neither might they turne them out.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Then in ſuch caſe it would bee in the Officers power to tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize even to the higheſt extent their owne luſt ſhould lead them to, without any juſt authority on earth to queſtion or reſtraine them; for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:158481:6"/> if their Presbytery, their officiating, their governing, ruling, be by divine Right, and not the peoples free choice; however they behave themſelves in it, they cannot be turned out by the people.</p>
            <p>But how doth it appeare that they have their Office or Elderſhip immediately from God? Is it ſufficient for them to ſay ſo? Then may any other number of their Brethren pretend the like.</p>
            <p>He alleadges 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 20. <hi>Now then we are Ambaſſadours for Chriſt as though God did beſeech you by us: We pray you in Chriſts ſtead be yee reconciled to God:</hi> But may not ſo many Tinkers uſe the very ſame Text, and ſaying they are Chriſts Ambaſſadours, thruſt themſelves o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any Congregation in the world if this be faire dealing? If there goes no more thereunto but confidence and laying claime, hee that can juſtle hardeſt will doubtleſſe get it, though <hi>Simon Magus</hi> could not carry it with money.</p>
            <p>But what kinde of Ambaſſadours did <hi>Paul</hi> make himſelfe and thoſe Primitive Chriſtians to be? What power did they take upon them? And how farre? They were Chriſts Ambaſſadours; we know them by their entreating, mildneſſe, gentleneſſe and long-ſuffering, as in the ſame 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 20. with <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 1. 2. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 2. But the Prelaticall Presbytery, the pretended Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of Chriſt in theſe times, wee know to be Wolves that worry, ſterve or flea the very Lambes of Chriſt alive; and as if their cruelty were not ſatisfied with the deſtruction of their bodies, endeavour what they can, to put a yoake of bondage upon the very ſoules of their Brethren, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. from v. 28. to 31. <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. 25, 26. 3 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>The other place produced is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Let a man ſo account of us, as of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the myſteries of God;</hi> but the Presbyters which wee ſpeake of, inſtead of taking upon them a <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> lay claime unto a <hi>Juriſdiction, Dominion,</hi> a <hi>Prelaty;</hi> Inſtead of being Stewards, they command, require, expecting lordly obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſubmiſſion; They ſcorne to uſe entreating and beſeeching, as <hi>Paul</hi> the aged, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 1. 3. <hi>ſtet pro ratione voluntas</hi> is their motto, their ſymboll.</p>
            <p>Thus we may ſee the Texts produced to maintaine the Presbyteriall government to be of Divine Right, make eminently againſt it; neither is it more evident in Scripture, than from reaſon and experience, to wit, That what power the Presbyters have and exerciſe, they have it from man, and not immediately from God, ſince the Brethren doe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:158481:7"/> either explicitly or implicitly make choice of them, and might as well have choſen any other if they had pleaſed: <hi>Church Officers are no more immediately from God, than Civill Officers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, <hi>Apollonius</hi> acknowledges the Presbyterie to bee the Repreſentative Church, but denies the meanes, without which I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet knew it pretended ſo much as poſſible to bee conſtituted: Firſt, he ſayes, <hi>Multitudo fidelium in Eccleſia poteſtatem regendi, &amp; ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictione ſpirituali negotia Eccleſiaſtica dijudicandi non habet jure Dei, proinde eam ſenioribus &amp; Preſbyteris delegare non poteſt: Hoc ſenſu igitur Repreſentativam Eccleſiam non agnoſcimus. Nec talem agnoſcimus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam Repreſentativam quae à multitudine fidelium miſſa, abſolutam pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem per leges &amp; juriſdictiones actus ſuos obligandi multitudinem ejus fidem &amp; conſcientias ſubjiciendi; ita ut abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> examine ut laudatum ſuſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peret quicquid ab hac Eccleſia ſtatutum foret. At Eccleſiam Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivam hanc ex ſacris literis agnoſcimus, quae eſt caetus Preſbyterorum à mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudine Eccleſiae electus, qui authoritate &amp; juriſdictione Eccleſiaſticâ à Chriſto accepta Eccleſiae praeeſt &amp; invigilat, &amp; decretis ſecundum ſacram Scripturam factis &amp; juriſdictione ſpirituali eam regit:</hi> which in effect is thus: Firſt, That Beleevers in generall have no power to judge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Church affaires, therefore they cannot give or derive unto the Presbyters what they themſelves never had; and ſecondly, that the Lawes of Country are not ſufficient to authoriſe Beleevers for chooſing Church Commiſſioners, who may afterwards oblige them and their conſciences by whatſoever decrees ſhall be by them agreed upon without examining it themſelves; But ſayes he, a Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church is an Aſſembly of Presbyters choſen by the multitude, who having received Eccleſiaſticall authority and juriſdiction from Chriſt, doe watch over the Church, and governe it according to the Scripture. To him therefore, or Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> that quotes him, I ſhould deſire to make theſe following Queries.</p>
            <p>The truth is, <hi>Apollonius</hi> acknowledges the Presbyterie to bee the Repreſentative Church, but denies the meanes, without which I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet knew it pretended ſo much as poſſible to bee conſtituted: Firſt, he ſayes, <hi>Multitudo fidelium in Eccleſia poteſtatem regendi, &amp; ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictione ſpirituali negotia Eccleſiaſtica dijudicandi non habet jure Dei, proinde eam ſenioribus &amp; Preſbyteris delegare non poteſt: Hoc ſenſu igitur Repreſentativam Eccleſiam non agnoſcimus. Nec talem agnoſcimus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam Repreſentativam quae à multitudine fidelium miſſa, abſolutam pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem per leges &amp; juriſdictiones actus ſuos obligandi multitudinem ejus fidem &amp; conſcientias ſubjiciendi; ita ut abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> examine ut laudatum ſuſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peret quicquid ab hac Eccleſia ſtatutum foret. At Eccleſiam Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivam hanc ex ſacris literis agnoſcimus, quae eſt caetus Preſbyterorum à mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudine Eccleſiae electus, qui authoritate &amp; juriſdictione Eccleſiaſticâ à Chriſto accepta Eccleſiae praeeſt &amp; invigilat, &amp; decretis ſecundum ſacram Scripturam factis &amp; juriſdictione ſpirituali eam regit:</hi> which in effect is thus: Firſt, That Beleevers in generall have no power to judge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Church affaires, therefore they cannot give or derive unto the Presbyters what they themſelves never had; and ſecondly, that the Lawes of Country are not ſufficient to authoriſe Beleevers for chooſing Church Commiſſioners, who may afterwards oblige them and their conſciences by whatſoever decrees ſhall be by them agreed upon without examining it themſelves; But ſayes he, a Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church is an Aſſembly of Presbyters choſen by the multitude, who having received Eccleſiaſticall authority and juriſdiction from Chriſt, doe watch over the Church, and governe it according to the Scripture. To him therefore, or Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> that quotes him, I ſhould deſire to make theſe following Queries.</p>
            <p>At what time doe the Presbyters receive their Church power from Chriſt? By what meanes and mediation? Whether before they be choſen Presbyters or afterwards? If before; Whether did this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer lye idle in them till they became Presbyters? And might it not poſſibly have continued ſo all their life time, if they had never beene choſen Presbyters, or are they predeſtinated to bee choſen, when Chriſt has once made a deed of gift unto them of ſome conſiderable proportion of ſpirituall power? But if we ſee they cannot exerciſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:158481:7"/> any ſpirituall power untill they be choſen Presbyters, and that wee might have choſen others as well as they; Doe you thinke the people will ever bee brought to thinke they have any other juriſdiction than what they give, and ſuffer them to enjoy? Whether doe the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ever part from their ſpirituall power after they have once recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it? and how come they to loſe poſſeſſion and the exerciſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ever after? Surely if theſe Queries be well anſwered, all the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer the Presbyters have, beſides what the people derive unto them, will be one of the ſtrongeſt phantaſticall deluſions and Chimera's which ever yet was heard of.</p>
            <p>But becauſe you make ſo much of <hi>Apollonius,</hi> ſince he is upon the Stage, if the indifferent Reader pleaſe to runne over theſe few fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing paſſages, he will not only finde him contradict himſelfe, but Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> alſo in the very title and whole ſubject matter of his Book: Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> throughout this volumne of his affirmes and endeavours to prove, that, <hi>Princes and Parliaments have the ſole ſoveraigne and legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power in all matters of Religion both for Diſcipline and Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the contrary <hi>Apollonius</hi> ſayes it is in Eccleſiaſticall Aſſemblies and Synods in theſe words, c. 6. p. 107. <hi>Competit ex jure Dei Eccleſiis in Claſſibus &amp; Synodis junctis, poteſtas Canones legeſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Eccleſiaſticas fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendi, quae omnes Eccleſias particulares unius Provinciae aut Regni con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringunt ad obedientiam:</hi> which is in effect, That, Eccleſiaſticall Aſſemblies, Synods, have by <hi>Divine Right</hi> a power of making Canons and Eccleſiaſticall Lawes which doe binde unto obedience all the particular Churches of a Province or Kingdome, (he may as well ſay of all the world:) and p. 109. He tells us that, <hi>That <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of particular Churches in Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline and Government common to them all, which is exerciſed in Synods and Claſſes, is of Divine Right, and propoſed to us in the example of the Apoſtolicall Church, for imitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus is <hi>Apollonius</hi> point blanke in oppoſition to Mr. <hi>Pryn;</hi> neither is he at better agreement with himſelfe, for p. 108. He ſayes, <hi>The po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Synods doth not take away or diſturb the Eccleſiaſticall power and liberty of particular Churches; but ſerves to direct, conſerve and promote their Eccleſiaſticall power and liberty, that they may become more efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, powerfull and fit to edifie;</hi> and yet p. 144. He ſayes; <hi>Claſſibus &amp; Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodis competit authoritativa quaedam inſpectio, &amp; judicium non tantum diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretionis ſed &amp; juriſdictionis &amp; approbationis in excommunicationibus à</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:158481:8"/> 
               <hi>particularibus Eccleſiis peragendis; ita ut nulla Eccleſia particularis quae communionem ſuam Eccleſiaſticam cum aliis Eccleſiis in Synodis &amp; Claſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus colit, aliquod ſuae communionis membrum excommunicare, &amp; Sathanae tradere legitimè poſſit abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Claſſis aut Synodi authoritativo judicio &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probatione:</hi> that is, There is due to Claſſes and Synods a certaine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorative inſpection and judgement, not only of diſcretion, but alſo of juriſdiction and approbation in excommunications to bee paſſed by particular Churches; ſo that no particular Church which keepes Eccleſiaſticall fellowſhip with other Churches aſſembled in a Synod may lawfully excommunicate or deliver up to Sathan any of their members, without the authoritative judgement and approbation of the Synod; and to mend the matter he yet tells us, p. 108. <hi>That the power which particular Churches have, is granted them immediatly from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od, not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived unto them by Synods;</hi> as alſo, <hi>that the power of Synods is granted them immediately from God, not derived to them from particular Churches:</hi> which is as much as if he had ſaid, that each of them muſt bee Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent and abſolute of it ſelfe; and yet one muſt ſubmit unto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; contradiction upon contradiction, or elſe I underſtand it not.</p>
            <p>But to returne againe to Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> himſelfe; who would thinke that any one who had but the head-piece of a man, much leſſe one that takes upon him to be a Champion, ſhould be ſo miſerably tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with vain-glory as thus to play the Bragadocio, and fill the world with bookes and pamphlets as if hee had got the victory, or ſpoken ſomewhat to the purpoſe, when yet it may appeare upon due ſearch of an indifferent judge, that neither in the whole catalogue of his bookes which was lately printed, nor in whatſoever came ſince to light, will there be found ſo much as one leafe truly worth reading, or any whit availing him in this controverſie which he (not without recanting in his owne heart I beleeve by this time, to ſee he thrives no better in it) hath undertaken againſt the Independents; remaining ſtill ſo ſhameleſſe, that not being able to conceale, or any longer to uphold his vaine undertaking, flyes unto the High Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, endeavouring to exaſperate their power againſt ſuch, whoſe prayers and contributions, in likelihood, have been the only, or chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt meanes to keepe him thus long alive?</p>
            <p>But alas, what can we expect of this volumne of Civill-Common-Law-Divinity of yours, when you acknowledge it to be <hi>diſtracted ſubitane</hi> collections, <hi>indigeſted nocturnall lucubrations</hi> (you may like
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:158481:8"/> enough ſay dreames) borrowed from the houres allotted to your ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary naturall reſt, <hi>Epiſt. Dedic.</hi> One would have thought the Anſwerer of your ſubitane apprehenſions digeſted into 12 conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſerious queſtions, when you confeſſed, you had neither leiſure nor opportunity, had given you a ſeaſonable and ſufficient <hi>item,</hi> not to trouble the world with ſuch traſh againe; and yet you are not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſay you publiſhed them principally for ſatisfaction of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſuch as moſt ſeduce the ignorant; when doubtleſſe ſuch lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as this of yours, is good for nothing elſe but to ſeduce the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, who more admire a margent full of ruſty antick Authours, than whole leaves and chapters of arguments and ſound reaſon; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your own arguing you do hereby as you think, with your indigeſted readings of ſuperſtitious Popiſh writers, enable ſuch, as you call learned, ſtill farther to ſeduce the ignorant.</p>
            <p>You tell the Parliament in your Epiſtle Dedicatory, that <hi>having had the honour of vindicating their ſovereigne power in all Civill and Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary affaires, you expected a</hi> quietus eſt <hi>from all other coutroverſies concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the juriſdiction of Parliaments eſpecially in Eccleſiaſticall matters:</hi> Surely you might have ſaid with as much truth and reaſon, that having vindicated the ſovereigne power of the Roman Emperours, ſuppoſe the perſecuting <hi>Nero, Domitian, Trajan,</hi> or who elſe lived in any of the Apoſtles or Primitive times, you had likewiſe vindicated their legiſlative power in matters of Chriſtianity, about propagating the Goſpell, &amp;c. juſtifying them in putting to death our Saviour, and ſo many of his Saints: The juſt rights and power of Magiſtrates, are to all Magiſtrates alike; all one, whether they be Chriſtian or Pagan: Their power is given them as Magiſtrates, not as Chriſtians; and the ſubjection which we were commanded in the Goſpell, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 12. 13. to render them, was as to Heathen Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, ſince at that time there were no other.</p>
            <p>But why tro doe you ſay, how <hi>moſt men imagined that controverſies about the Parliaments juriſdiction in Eccleſiaſticall matters had been put to eternall ſilence, when our lordly Prelates loſt their votes and ſeſſion in Parliament by a publique law?</hi> Did you not intend that Presbyters ſhould ſucceed Biſhops? or did you thinke them to be leſſe lordly than their Reverend Fathers from whom they ſpring? Surely you ſhow your ſelfe very ignorant of the Presbyterians pretences, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour much to conceale them.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:158481:9"/>
            <p> Meethinks you might have ſeen a Pamphlet entituled <hi>The readineſſe of the Scots advance into England,</hi> wherein, beſides others, is a letter bearing date the 6 of <hi>November,</hi> 1643. from <hi>Edenborough,</hi> upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion as it relates of certaine propoſitions made by the <hi>French</hi> Agent unto the Privy Councell there, which ſayes, <hi>The Generall Aſſembly is ſubordinate to no Civill judicature whatſoever, &amp;c.</hi> And becauſe I finde Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> ſo captious, and apt to ſeeke <hi>ſubterfugies;</hi> leſt he ſhould caſt this off as the bare aſſertion of ſome <hi>Anonimous,</hi> he may, if hee pleaſe, finde not a little to the ſame purpoſe in <hi>A. Stewards</hi> Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Annotations upon the Apologeticall Narration, in theſe words; <hi>The Civill Magiſtrate arrogates not unto himſelfe</hi> (not ſo much as) <hi>any directive power in matters of Religion,</hi> p. 5. <hi>The Civill Magiſtrate arrogates no ſpirituall authority to himſelfe,</hi> p. 48. <hi>The Parliament indeed is the ſupreme Judicature, ſevere Tribunall, the moſt ſacred Refuge, &amp;c. in Civill cauſes, but it pretends no directive power in matters of Religion, by teaching, or preaching, or judging of controverſies of Religion, nor any exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutive power that is intrinſecall to the Church, as in the vocation, depoſition, and ſuſpention of Miniſters, &amp;c. which are meerly ſpirituall,</hi> p. 6. <hi>If your meaning be that the Parliament ſhould judge between the Independents and Preſbyterians, you goe againſt the Parliaments intentions,</hi> ibid. and laſtly. <hi>For intrinſecall ſpirituall power, it is not in your power to grant the Civill Magiſtrate any at all; neither can you give him more ſpirituall obedience than Scripture permitteth you, or give him a part of the ſpirituall power which you have received of God: It is only in God who can give power therein to any man, we dare not be ſo bold,</hi> p. 28. All this the Anſwerer of your 12 conſiderable Queſtions, as you called them, auvertiſed you of in p. 26. And for <hi>Apollonius</hi> whom you ſo much glory in, as I told you a little before, he ſayes that both <hi>particular Churches, as well as Generall Aſſemblies have their authority immediately from God,</hi> p. 108. which diametricall variance amongſt theſe Presbyterian Champions, doubtleſſe muſt needs be ominous, and preſage no leſſe than ruine, ſo much more ſpeedier as they protract the reconciling them: In which reſpect if Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> would be ſo good for the Goſpels ſake, as to give the Independents reſt, and take <hi>A. S.</hi> with <hi>Apollonius</hi> to taske; who knowes but that they may doe ſome good upon one another? I am ſure it were not more than needfull, each of their phanſies abounding with excreſcencies, which they might much advantage each other in cutting off.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:158481:9"/>
            <p> But what availeth it to have the head of one lordly Epiſcopall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late cut off, when a Hydra, a multitude, above 77 times as many Presbyteriall Prelates ſucceed inſtead thereof? <hi>Prelatia, Prelaty, Prelacy,</hi> as we uſe it vulgarly, is a preferring one before another; and the Presbyteriall government is much more truly ſaid to be Prelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, than either Epiſcopall or Papall; unleſſe you will ſay that neither Epiſcopall nor Papall be Prelaticall at all; for in either of thoſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments there are but few Prelates; but in the other there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; to wit, ſo many Prelates as there are Presbyters, each whereof is an abſolute Prelate, that is one preferred above his Brethren.</p>
            <p>You ſpeake of the defunct Prelates ſoules tranſmigrated into the <hi>Independents,</hi> acknowledging them for the moſt part <hi>really cordiall in their affections, actions to the Parliament and Church of England, for which, and for their piety,</hi> you ſay, <hi>they are to be highly honoured:</hi> But mee thinks this amounts to little leſſe than contradiction; Can the earthly Tabernacles of Independents, with the defunct Prelates ſoules in them make men of piety, cordiall in their affections, actions to the Parliament, and Church of England highly to bee honoured? I wiſh Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> would tell me whether it were the Prelaticall ſoules, or their earthly Tabernacles for whoſe ſake he caſts this grand <hi>Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium</hi> on them: Doubtleſſe the ſoule muſt have preheminence of the body, unleſſe your minde bee altered, and hold the <hi>immortality of the ſoule,</hi> which you ſeemed to diſcountenance in your 12 <hi>Inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſerious Queſtions,</hi> p. 7. But if <hi>Independents</hi> having Prelaticall ſoules in their earthly Tabernacles are for the moſt part <hi>men of piety highly to be honoured;</hi> why ſhould not the Prelates bee ſo too? The truth is, I cannot deny but Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> was once by more then a many and they godly too, held to be a man of piety, and was highly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured; in whoſe books and pamphlets, notwithſtanding, which have been publiſhed of late, may be obſerved, more corrupted prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and a far worſe ſpirit of perſecution, than ever was diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the late Delinquent decapilated Archbiſhop, from his firſt aſcending unto his higheſt growth of authority and greatneſſe; and in the Diary of his life, which I ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> printed not to do him honour (though after ages will not be tyed to be no wiſer than Mr. <hi>Pryn)</hi> I finde ſuch eminent ſignes of a morall noble pious minde, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſuch weake principles as hee had beene bred up in, (his owne perſecuting diſpoſition diſabling him from being inſtructed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:158481:10"/> better;) and particularly ſo ingenuous a paſſage in his Funerall Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon whereby he juſtifies the Parliament in putting him to death, as I may ſafely profeſſe unto all the world, I never could yet diſcerne any thing neare of like piety or ingenuity to be in Mr. <hi>Pryn,</hi> by all that ever I yet heard of him from firſt to laſt, or by all the bookes of his which ever came to may hands, wherein yet I have hitherto done him the honour in being at charges to buy as many, I meane one of every ſort, as I could ever meet withall.</p>
            <p>But I wiſh ſeriouſly that both Presbyteriall Prelates, and all others now ſurviving, who are any wayes poſſeſſed with this unruly ſpirit, this <hi>legion</hi> of perſecution, would, even for their owne ſakes, not ſo ſuddenly forget the little late Arch-Prelate, though his head bee off; ſince for my part, through ſome ſmall knowledge and experience of him both in his life and death, I am fully ſatisfied, that his endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſubvert the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome, and intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing another Religion, for which he was charged, and ſuffered death, aroſe only from that depraved principle of enduring no body of any other Religion or opinion but his owne: I hope both Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> and others of the ſame alay may thinke it worth revolving in their ſaddeſt thoughts: Perſecuters are worſe than birds and beaſts of rapine amongſt the reſt, whom even <hi>Nature</hi> teaches to aſſociate and joyne together againſt this common and moſt peſtilent of all enemies: Beares and Lions are not ſo hurtfull in a Country, as a miſguided zeale growne furious, is torrent like, and carries all before it: Such whoſe Religion teaches to perſecute, or but prevailes upon to make uſe of Civill coercive meanes for differences of Religion of Opinion, will eaſily be carried on from one degree unto another, untill their ends be compaſſed, whether by fire or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Gun-powder-plots, or Maritim Invaſions; <hi>Nothing comes amiſſe to them whom Religion once innitiates with the cruelties of compelling con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis worth obſerving, how whileſt the truth conſtrained Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> to acknowledge the <hi>Independents piety, with their reall and cordiall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and actions unto the Parliament and Church of England</hi> in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the Parliament, he tells them only that they are <hi>juſtly to bee blamed as great diſturbers of our publicke peace and unity</hi> (the better to amuſe them) whilſt in his other pamphlets and this farraginous hotch-potch of obſolet, Anticke Popiſh Hiſtories and Preſidents, for the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:158481:10"/> moſt part, which perhaps he thinks few or none of them will vout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to read through, he ſeeks to captivate and poyſon the peoples un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding into an evill conception of the Independents, and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe them, whileſt he himſelfe exclames, traduces, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes them, unto his power, with fire and fagot, meerly for nothing but becauſe they ſue and ſeeke for, in all humility and meekneſſe, a poſſibility of keeping a good conſcience both towards God and man; This is all they deſire as touching Eccleſiaſticall matters; let Mr. <hi>Pryn,</hi> who thinks himſelfe to have deſerved ſo well of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, become their Advocate, procure but thus much for them, and take the reſt for his fees.</p>
            <p>He flouriſhes, and cryes out againſt the <hi>Arminians</hi> of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> about aſcribing, at the firſt, unto the Civill Magiſtrate, a power of paſſing ultimate judgements in all controverſies of Faith and other Eccleſiaſticall matters ariſing in the Church; and afterwards con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting or denying ſuch a power belonging to the Civill Magiſtrate: Might he not even as well, nay much better blame former Parliaments of <hi>England</hi> for firſt acknowledging the Pope head of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, and afterwards renouncing of the Pope (much againſt his <hi>Holineſſe</hi> his good liking no doubt) to chooſe <hi>Henry</hi> 8. in his ſtead? And if <hi>Henry</hi> 8. then but a Papiſt were a fit Head of the Church; Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was no leſſe: (though the Papiſts cry out of a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall Head of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as much as Proteſtants of a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall Pope of <hi>Rome)</hi> and then ſurely King <hi>Charles</hi> muſt have ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this Headſhip of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and here I deſire to leave him, and yet to finde him here rather than a Presbyterian Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodall Head, untill Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> reſolve me what it is to be <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church; what his Power and Authority is over the Churches Body; whether the Body may or can doe any thing without the Head: And whether any, or what power one member or part of the Body hath over another: But before you put pen to paper, or your paper to the Preſſe at leaſt, that you will remember how King <hi>Charles</hi> the only ſupreme Head of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church according to the oath of Supremacy, is now at <hi>Oxford,</hi> with ſuch, and ſo great a part of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nationall Church, which if they ſhould call ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Aſſemby of Divines would likely paſſe judgement in ſundry points of Faith and other Eccleſiaſticall matters, quite contrary to the Parliament and Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:158481:11"/>
            <p> Page 29. of your Diſcourſe you quote a paſſage out of the laſt Convocation Canons that had the <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the tayle, which you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of, ſaying; <hi>The power to call and diſſolve Councels both</hi> Nationall <hi>and</hi> Provinciall <hi>is the true right of all Chriſtian Kings within their owne Realmes or Territories:</hi> Now if this be ſo; to what purpoſe doe the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> ſpend time in ſitting there? Why ſhould the Commonwealth be at 4s. a day charges for each of them? Why do they not repaire unto their flocks? Where will King <hi>Charles</hi> his Writ appeare for ſummoning them? and for want thereof, will not all the paines they take be loſt? Might not therefore the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance and offence they give their Independent Brethren have well beene ſpared? Are not both Houſes of Parliament tacitly aſperſed by Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> for cauſing them thus to aſſemble without King <hi>Charles</hi> his Writ, and ſo againſt his true Rights and Prerogative Royall? and laſtly, if this be not an abſolute making void and null, whatſoever the Aſſembly ſhall conclude on, or the Parliament eſtabliſh by their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, beſides a juſtifying of the Independents for not ſubmitting thereunto, let Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> himſelfe upon review be judge: For certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it will ſeeme ſtrange to every body elſe, how Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> producing, beſides others, in page 25, 26, 27, 28, 29. no leſſe than foure of King <hi>Charles</hi> his letters, only to prove the due right of Chriſtian Princes for calling ſuch Aſſemblies, can any wayes make legall the preſent ſitting of the Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> or how he can make atonement for himſelfe to give occaſion that both their aſſembling and whole proceedings may thus be called in queſtion.</p>
            <p>But p. 88. you bring in a Parentheſis (which doubtleſſe the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly will thinke had far better beene left out) that <hi>the aſſent of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy is only by way of aſſiſtance and advice, not ſimply neceſſary to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments determining what is hereſie;</hi> however, for my part, I do not much diſſent with you therein; and if the Aſſembly did like as well thereof, ſhould thinke it might ſomewhat qualifie their over forward and eager appetites, which elſe might too likely lead them to declare thoſe wayes hereticall, after which <hi>Paul</hi> was not aſhamed to ſay hee worſhipped the God of his Fathers, Act. 24. 14.</p>
            <p>But may not both Kings and Parliaments reprove you (like an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky Cow, who having given great quantity of milke kicks it downe with her foot) for contradicting your ſelfe, and plundring them ſo ſpeedily of all Eccleſiaſticall power which before in a good
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:158481:11"/> mood you caſt upon them ſo liberally without allowance, ſaying p. 141. That <hi>there is the ſelfe ſame reaſon and equity for ſeverall combined Churches in a Councell, Synod, Presbytery to have a coercive power over every particular Congregation in their limits, as for any particular Congregation to claime or exerciſe a juriſdiction in point of direction or correction, over any or every particular member of it.</hi> This aſſertion, I conceive, is yet more prodigious than all your Popiſh preſidents with which you ever were acquainted, and I beleeve that never any body hereafter will ſo much as acknowledge you in this opinion: Whereas the Title of your Booke and whole Diſcourſe in generall aſcribe all power and authority unto the Civill Magiſtrate both in Civill and Eccleſiaſticall matters; This paſſage gives the ſame unto a Synod, even a Coercive, that is, all Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and that both in Civill and Eccleſiaſticall matters, provided they doe but colour and call them Eccleſiaſticall, for nothing of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive can be otherwiſe than Civill properly: If you excuſe your ſelfe by ſaying you meant a Synod ratified by Authority of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I anſwer, that you muſt meane a Synod ſo ratified by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Parliament, as ſome Presbyterians of <hi>Scotland</hi> meane when they expect that Parliaments muſt doe it <hi>ex officio,</hi> whether they bee willing or unwilling; and if your meaning had been otherwiſe, you might have brought your compariſon betweene a Parliament and particular Congregations, not a Synod; beſides that, the power of direction, which you acknowledge to be in every particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation towards any or every member thereof, I doe not finde to bee granted them, or ſo much as medled with by Authority of Parliament; ſo likewiſe, if you will have it any wayes hold parallel, you muſt meane the Synods Canons ſo confirmed by authority of Parliament, as that the Parliaments confirmation muſt ſtill wait upon and follow the Synods beck and requiſition.</p>
            <p>That part of the Statute 37. <hi>H.</hi> 8. c. 17. which you bring to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the King Head of the Church, ſayes, That by Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>All</hi> Authority and Power is wholly given to him to heare and determine <hi>All</hi> manner of cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, and to correct <hi>All</hi> vice and ſinne whatſoever, and ſuch perſons as his Majeſty ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point thereunto: So that whereas a negative voice which hath beene, and is ſtill the great controverſie betwixt the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Civill matters only; this Statute 37. <hi>H.</hi> 8. c. 17. with Mr. <hi>Pryns</hi> opinion and conſequences thereupon, doe freely grant the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:158481:12"/> King in all ſpirituall cauſes and affaires: Surely if all <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> did agree with Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> in this particular; the King might like enough be willing for the preſent to part from his negative voice in Civill matters, in full aſſurance of regaining it in recompence of Pardons and Diſpenſations, which he might grant by virtue of his Headſhip of the Church, with the <hi>ſole</hi> authority of correcting all vice and ſinne, and finall determining all cauſes Eccleſiaſticall.</p>
            <p>The truth is, that Chriſtian Kings and Princes have <hi>de facto</hi> done much with Civill cenſures in maintenance of Religion, whether right or wrong, eſtabliſhed by Law: But the point is, what they did, or might doe lawfully, <hi>de jure:</hi> Whence is their power derived? Surely the power of Princes pretending to the name of Chriſtian, whether Papiſts, Lutherans, Calviniſts, Browniſts or Anabaptiſts, and even of Turkiſh and Pagan Princes is all alike: So that whatſoever power the beſt Reformed Princes can juſtly aſſume unto themſelves in Eccleſiaſticall affaires; even Popiſh Kings and the Great Turk may fully pretend and act as much in and about the Churches within their Territories, and neither of them be more diſobeyed or reſiſted than the other: <hi>The power is given to them as Magiſtrates and Princes, not as Chriſtians;</hi> otherwiſe they might be depoſed at any time if they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Antichriſtian, which is exploded for a Popiſh doctrine.</p>
            <p>But as <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> did not make that Decree for building of the Temple out of love or conſcience unto the God of <hi>Ezra, Ezra</hi> 7. from v. 21. to 26. So can it not be concluded from Kings and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates interpoſing their Civill power about matters meerly Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall, that therefore they might and did doe it by full authority from God; ſince by the ſelfe ſame manner of arguing, it would follow that Popery were the trueſt Religion, becauſe moſt Chriſtian Princes, as they are called, have eſtabliſhed Popery.</p>
            <p>But it may have beene obſerved, how Princes and Magiſtrates in all ages who have had the Sword of Juſtice in their keeping, have for the moſt part beene kept in an ignorant and ſuperſtitious over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awfulneſſe by the Clergy of thoſe times, who ſtill for their owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ends, prevailed with them to countenance and enforce their Conſtitutions by coercive meanes upon the people; by which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of theirs, both Prince and People became ſo entangled and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared to them by degrees; that if either of them afterwards ſought to withdraw themſelves forth from this bondage, they ſtill found ſuch a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:158481:12"/> party of the other, as was able to curb and bring them againe into ſubjection of Holy Church; as they pretended, though never ſo Popiſh or otherwiſe corrupt; And this <hi>ſeries</hi> of corrupted and corrupting preſidents with their tyrannicall dominion over mens faith and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> diſclaimed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 24. Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> produces as orthodox, requiring it ſhould bee eſtabliſhed after the manner of <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> irrevocable, and made very Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of; aſcribing by this Antick rabble of quotations as great a power unto the Civill Magiſtrate in ſpirituall matters as ever any Pope of Rome aſſumed unto himſelfe.</p>
            <p>But if the Civill Magiſtrate muſt be maſters of our faith, determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all controverſies in Church affaires; why, I pray, was Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> ſo refractory to the Biſhops who then were authoriſed by the Civill Magiſtrate of the united Kingdome, which now to the univerſall griefe, is ſo mortally divided? Theſe are hard queſtions I confeſſe; but Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> will get the more glory when hee knowes how to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer them.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Arminians</hi> upon the improving of their ſtudies about their other controverſies, or the Civill Magiſtrates bad imploying a power aſcribed, but not due to them, ſaw their errour and amended; muſt they be upbrayded? I would be loath that Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> ſhould want of ſuch encouragements of providence and mercy, leſt it might hinder his repentance of what, I feare mee, he is too highly guilty; God is contented to tole us to him and to his truth, even with variety of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticements and provocations: fraile mankinde is dull and ſtupid; no leſſe than Gods infinite wiſdome together with his unmeaſurable bounty will ſerve to animate and raiſe us up to new diſcoveries of knowledge and obedience.</p>
            <p>Take this then for your learning, that whoſoever attributes to any man or Magiſtrate, a power of impoſing any thing upon the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of others in matters of Religion, doe juſtifie them in whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they impoſe, though it be erroneous, ſo they impoſe according to their owne judgements and underſtandings, condemning the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for not ſubmitting, though it be unto erroneous impoſitions: for if the one may impoſe, his owne reaſon muſt teach him what he may impoſe; And if he have juſt authority to impoſe, the other is obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in conſcience to obey; and ſo by conſequence, ſhould be engaged to ſubmit implicitly to whatſoever ſuperſtitious ceremonies and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip were put upon him.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:158481:13"/>
            <p> In your Epiſtle to the Reader, you ſay the Independents may upon the ſame grounds deny the Catholicke Church, an article of the Creed, upon which they deny a Nationall Church; as though ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more particular Churches might not as well make one Catholick, as ſeverall, but yet ſo many fewer Nationall Churches; or as though particular Chriſtians who lived ſtragling in Turky or any Pagan Countries where they could not poſſibly be members of a Nationall Church, could not poſſibly be members of the Catholique Church.</p>
            <p>You accuſe the Independents as beleeving moſt things with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, according to their preſent light, with a liberty of changing as new light ſhall bee diſcovered to them: But did ever any man ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſhoot himſelfe? Certainly this is ſo high a character of the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents compleateſt poſture enſuring or growing ſtature in the Schoole of Chriſt, as could be applyed unto them, wherein they glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry not a little, and place it as the only ground-worke and foundation, without which they cannot grow in grace from one degree of faith unto another, untill they become perfect Men, perfect Saints, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 12, 13. and yet your Law-Divinity knowes no better, than to ſay, this is in truth to bring a <hi>Skepticiſme</hi> into Religion.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay their principles diſſolve all relations, all ſubordinations, and humane ſociety it ſelf: I anſwer, that this is even as if you ſhould affirme a Turke not to be a man, unleſſe he will bee a Chriſtian, unleſſe he will be a member of ſome Nationall Church; nay, of every Nationall Church, ſince his not being of any one is all alike prejudiciall or damageable: But they are the Presbyteriall and ſuch other Prelaticall tenets which deſtroy, and expreſſely murder all humane ſociety, in avouching as <hi>William Pryn</hi> with his <hi>enſe recidendum,</hi> and <hi>A. Stewart,</hi> does, that ſayes <hi>whoſoever is cut off or caſt out of the Church, muſt likewiſe be caſt out, and cut off from the Civill ſtate,</hi> p. 166. in 2. part of his Duply, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Sir, I confeſſe I have ſpent more time and paper about your Epiſtles than I intended, which if you and the Reader will but excuſe, I ſhall endeavour to make you amends in part by troubling you the leſſe with your ruſty, muſty rubbiſh of Popiſh times and preſidents.</p>
            <p>Page 1. Your firſt propoſition is, That <hi>the calling of Synods or Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies about Church matters belongs not to Biſhops, Miniſters, nor private or particular Congregations; but to Princes or ſupreme temporall Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:158481:13"/> 
               <hi>and Powers;</hi> So that if the Magiſtrate be Turkiſh under whoſe juriſdiction live many Proteſtant <hi>Greekes,</hi> I meane ſuch as diſavow the Pope with the greateſt part of his unſound doctrine; If he be Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh as the Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> with the Kings of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> in whoſe territories inhabit millions of Proteſtants, all which Proteſtants muſt never meet together in Synods and Aſſemblies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Church affaires, becauſe thoſe Emperours and Kings are never likely to ſummon Synods for them, or put them in minde to doe it themſelves.</p>
            <p>You ſtill quote multitudes of texts to prove your Propoſitions with, in hopes perhaps that if one faile you another may doe the deed; but you happen to be ſo ſucceſſeleſſe therin, as if you uſed ſtill to preſſe the Scriptures which came firſt to hand, ranking them in your margent whether they would or no; which 'tis true, has ſtood you in ſtead no more, than a <hi>forc't Militia</hi> does the King or Parliament; &amp; yet doubtles, that God with whom the Word was from the beginning, and who is the very Word, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 1. will not approve that his bleſſed Word ſhould be made uſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and imployed ſo vainly, impertinently, prepoſterouſly, raſhly, and irreverently: Wherefore I would gladly adviſe Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> for the future, to inſert the very words themſelves of every text hee quotes, in hopes that if he doe but once read them over by himſelfe, he will finde they make nothing to the purpoſe, and ſo have ingenuity enough to leave them out.</p>
            <p>After you have done belying <hi>ſacred</hi> Scripture, you flye for aſſiſtance unto <hi>prophane,</hi> and from thence tell us by whoſe authority the firſt Generall Councells were convocated; which proves nothing elſe, but that whether it be King or Parliament that have the ſtrongeſt ſword, or ſhall prevaile and get the better over the other in this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill War; the Aſſembly of Divines now at Weſtminſter muſt ſit no longer, not any of their coat ever meet againe above two in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, unleſſe the preſent ruling party pleaſe, leſt they be tearmed a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, and fall into a <hi>Pramunire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by what authority tro did the pretended Synod of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> aſſemble? <hi>Act.</hi> 15. What Kings or Parliaments Writs, or Letters-patents had they for ſo doing? What Court countenance did they procure to ſecond their proceedings? for my part, I had rather fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſuch a preſident, and erre with them, if you will needs eſteem it ſuch; than degenerate with the weaker Chriſtians of after ages, in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:158481:14"/> ſupplicating of Powers and Princes in ſuch a manner, whereby they ſhould be moved to thinke I granted them ſuch a power, as God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver gave them, or confirmed them in, ſuppoſing they had a juſt liberty of denying, what through want perhaps of Chriſtian courage only, or the Civill powers protection, I durſt not put in practice without their order and commiſſion.</p>
            <p>Page 4. I am glad to finde you acknowledging a paſſage of the Biſhops letters, wherein they return thanks to <hi>Valentinian</hi> and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> for aſſembling the Councell of <hi>Illirium,</hi> which ſayes, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t nemo deeſſet volens; nemo cog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur invitus;</hi> That no Biſhop might be abſent who was deſirous to be there, and none compelled who were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to be preſent; from whence followes an irrefragable conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that their Councells, Decrees or Canons, did not binde all people univerſally, but only ſuch as of their owne accords ſubmitted thereunto: If Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> will but procure the ſame juſt priviledge for his Independent Brethren, they will have the leſſe occaſion of excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, if he domineere over the volunteers of the Presbyterian party.</p>
            <p>Page 87. You ſay, <hi>The Statutes in Q.</hi> Maries <hi>dayes repealing divers Acts touching Religion in K.</hi> Edward 6. <hi>his Reigne, and ſetting up Maſſe and the old [Popiſh] Liturgies againe, doe ſufficiently evidence the juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of our Princes and Parliaments in matters of the Church and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;</hi> which is in effect; firſt, That this preſent Parliament, or any other hereafter have a juriſdiction to ſet up Popery againe, and ſo Judaiſme or Turciſme, even what they pleaſe; for all Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have equall power: And ſecondly, that if they doe ſet up Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, Judaiſme or Turciſme, that then all England muſt ſubmit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and conſequently become Papiſts, Jewes and Turkes (or Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites which is more worſe then either:) for whatſoever a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, eſpecially the ſupreme, has juriſdiction in, that, he may juſtly and lawfully put in execution; and that, the people may not diſobey, upon paine of ſinning, and danger of damnation, <hi>Rom</hi> 13. 2.</p>
            <p>But under what colour and pretence then did Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> refuſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection unto Church government by Epiſcopacy, and according to the Common-Prayer-Booke? Doe not take it ill that I ſpur the queſtion ſo ſoone unto you againe; I may aske it oft-times, before you will be able to anſwer once, without condemning your ſelfe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your principles and lawes, by which you proyoke juſtice againſt the Independents.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:158481:14"/>
            <p> Were not Epiſcopacy and the Common-Prayer-Booke eſtabliſhed by Act of Parliament, which had as great a power than as this preſent Parliament has now, or any other can have hereafter? Nay, you ſay expreſſely, p. 88. That <hi>the Statute,</hi> 1 Eliz. chap. 2. <hi>for uniformity of Common-Prayer and Service in the Church, and adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, enjoyning conformity under temporall and Eccleſiaſticall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is an irrefragable proofe of the Parliaments power in all Church mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters:</hi> What was it tro, that then encouraged you to withſtand the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of Parliaments when they agreed not with your owne humour and diſpoſition, which you now preſſe ſo violently upon the tender conſciences of your Independent Brethren? Can there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare any other clearer reaſon for it, to the apprehenſion of ſtanders by, moderate men even of Mr. <hi>Pryns</hi> beſt friends, or any that have their wits about them; than that Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> having ſuffered (for Chriſts cauſe as he thought, to thinke more charitably of him than he doth of others) upon falſe principles, grew weary of it, and reſolv'd that as the Biſhops domineer'd and perſecuted him; ſo he would repaire himſelfe by perſecuting others?</p>
            <p>But did the only wiſe God, thinke we, reſolve to create man after his owne Image, to eſtate him in ſuch a ſad and execrable condition, worſe then that of Beaſts, Wolves, Beares, and Tygres; as that hee muſt neceſſarily tyrannize, or be tyrannized over both in ſoul &amp; body? and yet it cannot poſſibly be otherwiſe, if you will grant a power to Kings, Parliaments or Synods to require conformity from others in any thing which is not agreeable to their conſciences; for if ſuch a latitude and height of juriſdiction be granted but to the more ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Kings, Parliaments and Synods; both <hi>Papiſts, Lutherans, Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> pretending and really taking themſelves to be the moſt orthodox, are bound in conſcience to lay claime to, and put in execution this power of compelling all the world unto their uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity; and ſo infallibly produce the moſt curſed enmity and hatred betwixt all people but differing in opinion, exceeding that of <hi>Canni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals;</hi> or the profoundeſt of antipathies between any irrationall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures whatſoever; and therefore you are mightily miſtaken p. 96. to be ſo confident that Independents would preach univerſall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſubjection under penalties Eccleſiaſticall and Civill, if the Parliament ſhould eſtabliſh an Independent government, which are clearly incompatible, and contradictory to themſelves and principles;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:158481:15"/> the ignorance whereof, though to ſome it may ſeeme as ſlight, as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily apprehended by a willing and enquiring ſpirit, I perſwade my ſelfe, hath not only tranſported Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> himſelfe, but many others into multitudes of impertinencies and abſurdities.</p>
            <p>Oh that Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> therefore, or any one of the Presbyterian way, who wiſhes well to godlineſſe, would but pleaſe to caſt an eye upon <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> chap. 10. and conſiderately give their opinion, <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be perſecuted be not even the moſt infallible marke of the true Church and Saints of Chriſt;</hi> notwithſtanding moſt Chriſtians thus perſecute one another.</p>
            <p>Page 94. and 109. You ſay the oppoſites to Parliaments Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall juriſdiction have formerly and more eſpecially in this preſent Parliament, addreſſed ſeverall petitions to this High and Honourable Court for Reformation of the Church, &amp;c. wherein, under favour, I conceive you have miſapprehended their proceedings and intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which doubtleſſe were for the moſt part, or beſt affected, that the Parliament, in whom they acknowledged the ſovereigne power to reſide, would permit, countenance and encourage all godly men of gifts in preaching downe Hereſies, errours, Idolatry, Popery, &amp;c. many whereof had either beene formerly eſtabliſhed by law, or not permitted to be preached downe through the Prelates corruption contrary to the Law.</p>
            <p>This is the beſt, even all the Reformation, which the Civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, as Civill, has a capacity of compaſſing againſt all Hereſies and errours, which muſt neceſſarily be vanquiſhed by the ſword of the Spirit, and cannot poſſibly be ſuppreſſed by carnall weapons or the Civill ſword; they may deſtroy the fleſh, but cannot properly be ſaid to touch and worke upon the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Page 109. After a franticke, infectious, peſtilentiall feaver-fit of rayling, the likeſt that of <hi>Billingſgate,</hi> you tell Mr. <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> with much gravity, forſooth, but far more ſaucie ignorance, that it was no leſſe than <hi>high preſumption</hi> for him, being a meere Divine, and a man altogether ignorant of, or unskilfull in the ancient Rights and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of our Parliament (as his writings demonſtrate, and himſelfe intimates, page 5.) to undertake and determine, to judge of them ſo peremptorily, and in ſuch manner as he has done, &amp;c. But how come you tro, a meere Lawyer (I wiſh you were good at that, at any thing) to take ſo much upon you in Divinity, (if Divinity and the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:158481:15"/> knowledge of Parliamentary priviledges be inconſiſtent, as you ſeeme to inſinuate) to pin the Goſpel with its propagation and whole affaires upon Civill powers; the greateſt ſhare, or major part, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (which ſhould both by your politie and divinity be ſubmitted to) is in the hands of <hi>Turkes</hi> of <hi>Infidels?</hi> where's your licence from the Court of Heaven for ſubjugating the <hi>Goſpell of peace</hi> to your <hi>litigious law-caſes and preſidents,</hi> moſt whereof are all Popiſh? To ſacrifice the Scriptures, the Word, even God himſelfe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 1. whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, both Diſcipline and Doctrine unto Acts of Parliaments, which have beene heretofore ſo Popiſh, and may poſſibly be ſo againe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; to which according to your grounds, the whole Kingdome muſt conforme and be obedient not only paſſively but actively, and that for conſcience ſake?</p>
            <p>But what lawfull calling or warrant have you (if a man may be ſo bold with you as you are with other men) from Gods Word, or our Lawes, to handle the Juriſdiction and Rights of Parliament more then Mr. <hi>Goodwin?</hi> Was not his <hi>Imprimatur</hi> as legall or authenticall as yours? Doe you thinke the Parliament had not far rather heare the ſubmiſſive cautions and mementoes of a loving tender and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate remembrancer, as in the preſence of the God of Heaven, whoſe duty is to <hi>teach all Nations, Matth.</hi> 28. 19. as occaſion is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, from Parliament to peaſant; than be flattered and ſoothed up with fuſty ſweepings of Popiſh preſidents, by one, who yet (I think) pretends to be (no Canon but) a Proteſtant Lawyer, beſt vers'd at Common-pleas and Chancery bills? Certainly 'tis none of Mr. <hi>Pryns</hi> leaſt overſights thus to bring himſelfe, a Lawyer, whoſe wrangling faculty ſets and keeps all people at worſe war amongſt themſelves, than all forreigne enemies can do, with Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> whoſe zeale, piety, and fervent interceding towards the Throne of Grace for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling unto the God of peace, not only all ſuch as joyne with him, but whoſoever elſe are capable thereof, hath beene heretofore, and is at preſent well knowne to all the godly and well affected in or about the City both far and neare, which does and ſtill will tend ſo much more to Mr. <hi>Pryns</hi> great reproach and infamy, for thus ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully traducing him?</p>
            <p>If Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> were a man truly godly and conſcientious, he might long ere this time have conſidered the unlawfulneſſe of his very Calling, according to the greateſt part of Lawyers practiſe, in enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:158481:16"/> more cauſes than they can poſſibly take care of as they ought, in taking of exceſſive fees, prolonging ſuites, and ſo involving the whole Kingdome in their ſophiſticall quirkes, tricks and quille<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, as that a man can neither buy nor ſell, ſpeake nor doe any thing, but he muſt be lyable to fall into their talons, without ever being able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme himſelfe; the Lawyers having moſt of their myſteries written in a little leſſe then heathen language, and detaining us in ſuch igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance or captivity, as that we may not plead nor underſtand our own caſes; by which and ſuch like deviſes of theirs, they are become the greateſt grievance, crying loudeſt to Heaven for juſtice to be done up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them by this Parliament, next to the corrupted depraved Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p>Page 153. When you are told that <hi>the Apoſtolicall Church of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, Act.</hi> 15. (improperly by you and all Popiſh writers call'd a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, and Grand preſident for Synods) <hi>was infallible, and therefore might ſay it pleaſed the Holy Ghoſt and them; and that, ſince you cannot ſay of whatſoever you ſhall doe, that it doth infallibly pleaſe the Holy Ghoſt, and for that cauſe may not be permitted to make binding determinations:</hi> you anſwer (moſt appoſitly no doubt) that <hi>the Apoſtles preacht by an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible ſpirit,</hi> ergo, <hi>none ought to preach but ſuch as have alike infallible ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with the Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I wonder Mr. <hi>Pryns</hi> wits are thus a wool-gathering; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that he proclaimes it to the world ſo much; for I muſt needs ſay, I never knew them otherwiſe! Cannot you let Independents preach by way of inſtruction, advice, &amp;c. though you were not ſure whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have the Holy Ghoſt or no; as well as they give you leave to do the like if you can; yea, to ſit and vote in Parliaments and Synods, enacting Ordinances, Decrees, and what you pleaſe, even as much as your pretended Synod of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (call it a Parliament too if you will) ſince there is no remedy, though to my knowledge you are brim full of little elſe than all fallibility? But when you have attained to be a Parliament or Synod-man, doe no more than that Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call infallible Aſſembly of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did; ſay, we doe well if we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your Ordinances and Decrees; and if we doe not, we may doe better, and therein be confident you ſay well infallibly: Thus you heare how you may become a Synod-man, and how your Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Brethren may eaſily have leave to preach, though neither of you be infallible; Let your Decrees and Ordinance paſſe as <hi>peaceably</hi> as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:158481:16"/> their Sermons, and both may lodge together, and likelier become friends the ſooner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 4. 22. We finde the pretended Synod ſtiled a Church [that is the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem]</hi> if a Church, it muſt have Church officers, that is, ruling and teaching Elders and Deacons; which I doe not perceive obſerved in any Synod ſince, nor can poſſibly be, unleſſe they can turne the fixed Churches of any particular place into Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods; and if that could be done, what would this be otherwiſe than for one ſiſter-Church to make and impoſe Canons and Decrees, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to you principles, upon all other ſiſter-Churches?</p>
            <p>Now and then, 'tis true, you refreſh us with an ingenuous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, which if you did but follow cloſe, would cleare your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding from multitudes of groſſe errours, and unparallel'd miſtakes.</p>
            <p>You acknowledge a <hi>poſſibility of erring, or ſome actuall errours in Councels, Synods, Parliaments, and that ſuch as apparently erronious and repugnant unto Scriptures may be diſobeyed:</hi> And now I ſee you have almoſt ſatisfied one of the 8 Queries in anſwer to your 12 conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſerious Queſtions, which hitherto I thought you had not beene able to give the leaſt ſatisfaction to, becauſe I heard it not in Print cry'd up and downe the ſtreets, a priviledge which any thing, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing of Mr. <hi>Pryns</hi> enjoyes peculiarly.</p>
            <p>But this ſhort acknowledgement of yours, if you underſtand what you ſay, and ſticke to it, will undoubtedly bring you over unto the Independents.</p>
            <p>And now (that your booke, and ſuch as read it over may make a comfortable end) ſince you are ſo good to grant a little, you ſhall ſee the Independents will comply with you, and ſay they'l aske no more: They only deſire it may be lawfull for them to diſobey your Councells, Synods, Parliaments when they actually erre, and are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently repugnant unto Scripture: But now, when they tell you ſo at any time, and challenge this free grant of yours, profeſſing in the preſence of God and Men, that they ſpeake the truth and lie not, their conſcience bearing witneſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 1. unleſſe you will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Chriſtianity in practiſe, you muſt beleeve them, and not mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure their conſciences and underſtandings by your owne, leſt they come ſhort of their due; you muſt not be both judge and party: no, nor judge only, where all ought to be Brethren, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. 8. Their <hi>owne</hi> reaſon muſt guide them: Their <hi>owne</hi> underſtanding muſt bee
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:158481:17"/> the ultimate reſolver of their wills; and none but their <hi>owne</hi> faith can ſave them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 4. 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 12. From the non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubmitting unto ſome Councells, Synods, and Parliaments, which you perhaps may not thinke erronious, will follow no other worſe conſequence, than this; That a man may likewiſe refuſe to heare or not believe ſome Sermons, which you perhaps may hold worth hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and neceſſary to be beleeved (though others as wiſe and godly as your ſelfe, doe thinke the contrary) which you may well be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent as to grant your Independent Brethren, ſince they will doe the like for you, expecting with long-ſuffering untill you be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd, or you convince them, <hi>peaceably.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 154. You proceed and ſay, admit Synods, Councells, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments have ſometimes erred out of human frailty; yet this is a moſt certaine truth, that they are not ſo apt to erre, as private men, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles of perſons leſſe learned, leſſe experienc'd, &amp;c. But this may not paſſe for orthodox neither, if, <hi>not many wiſe, not many learned are called,</hi> be Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 20. 26. beſides, experience teaches us, that God doth not diſcover his truth by whole-ſale, nor to whole Nationall Churches or Generall Councells at once, but rather by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and that for the moſt part, at firſt, to ſome contemptible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, perhaps, in the eyes of the world, who had no earthly ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or ſo much as any naturall preheminence to tempt or to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw him from being Gods Ambaſſadour or Trumpeter to publiſh it unto a people or whole Nation, it may be, not without his utmoſt perill.</p>
            <p>And beſides; doe we not finde that even theſe more learned, of whom the Councells and Synods are pretended to be compacted, are they, who moſt of all deceive? Are they not by their unſanctified human learning and wiſdome, the better enabled; nay, doe they not by that meanes become like ſo many decoy's to lead the multitude, the rabble after them over hedge and ditch, and, too too often, into the very ditch it ſelfe?</p>
            <p>But what if Synods, Councells and Parliaments were leſſe apt to erre, and beſt qualified to diſcover Truth, and debate matters of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie? It will not follow from thence, that either of them may therefore impoſe their ſuppoſed Truthes (for other than ſuppoſe they cannot be, for want of infallibility) or finall determinations upon the other: If there were a neceſſity that the greater part ſhould have this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:158481:17"/> ſpirituall dominion, or rather a Civill power in a ſpirituall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment over the leſſer, or the leſſer over the greater; then there might be ſome colour for the greater to have precedencie in ſome reſpects: But ſince either of them would be abſolutely ſinfull, we muſt grant it unto neither.</p>
            <p>Page 155. You ſay, That <hi>though it cannot be proved that all the Elders, Brethren, and whole Church of Jeruſalem were infallibly inſpired, yet they all ſaid it ſeemeth good to the Holy Ghoſt and them:</hi> To which I anſwer, that their ſaying ſo, was an infallible ſigne that all of them were then, as concerning what they affirmed, infallibly inſpired; otherwiſe, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Brethren with the reſt of the Church, but the Apoſtles alſo might poſſibly have told a lie, in ſaying ſo, in joyning with them in one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon verdict, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. v. 23. Nay, it might even now, and ever may be ſaid hereafter to the end of the world, that this paſſage in the Acts of the Apoſtles, <hi>It ſeemeth good to the Holy Ghoſt and us,</hi> is not of infallible truth, unleſſe, that both the Apoſtles, Brethren, and whole Church had beene infallibly aſſiſted in ſaying ſo; They ſpake not One for All, but All of them in One, or One Spirit, even God himſelfe, who is One, in All of them infallible: Say but as much, and upon as good grounds and reaſon, in behalfe of the Synod which ſits now at Weſtminſter, and you ſay ſomething: but for your great promiſe under the Goſpell, that God will powre out his Spirit upon <hi>all fleſh;</hi> ſurely it makes as much for Independents, unleſſe you ſuppoſe them to be ſome New-found Land-fiſh: But you yeeld it may be objected, how <hi>perhaps all or the greateſt part of the Parliament and Aſſembly are not endued with the ſanctifying Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, therefore they cannot uſe this language,</hi> [It ſeemeth good to the Holy Ghoſt and us:] This objecting of yours I confeſſe is ſomewhat ingenious; but alas! it ſeemes, you deſire not to continue ſo, in that you take ſuch paines in ſhruging and ſhifting to evade the force and truth thereof, by ſaying, <hi>'Tis only knowne to God who are his;</hi> and <hi>admit there may be ſome few among them, who have not Gods ſanctifying Spirit, yet I doubt not but very many, if not the major part of them have:</hi> Is not this profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered? Thouſands of conſcientious godly people object, how it is poſſible that all, or the greateſt part of the Parliament and Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly may not be indued with the ſanctifying Spirit of God; and Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> pretends to anſwer them by ſaying, <hi>he doubts not but they have:</hi> Is he not a doughty champion? But what if it ſhould be objected, that it may yet more fully, than by perchance, be ſaid, it cannot be made appeare that there is ſo much as one, neither in the Parliament nor Aſſembly,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:158481:18"/> who have had an infallible aſſiſtance of the ſanctifying Spirit, in any thing they have done already, or ſhall ever doe hereafter? and muſt we then neceſſarily be of their Religion, of their faith implicitly? yet we ſubmit, you ſee, unto them in Civill matters; our eſtates, our lives, and what ever we have that is mortall, has beene devoted, if not ſacrificed to juſtifie their power, and our ſubjection, but the reſt muſt be reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for him only, who is Lord Paramont of ſpirits as well as fleſh.</p>
            <p>Surely, Mr. <hi>Pryn,</hi> 'tis no ſmall diſſervice which you doe both Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Aſſembly, in thus expoſing their proceedings to be queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by no little, and that the moſt conſcionable and beſt affected party of the Kingdome; ſuch ſpirits of contention, as this of yours, were thoſe which made the firſt great breach amongſt the Parliaments friends; I meane, betwixt the Independents and Presbyterians; and now your ſelfe as the chiefe Ring-leader has begun a ſubdiviſion, even among the Presbyterians, by attributing (after ſuch an imperious and reproaching manner towards all ſuch as diſſent from your opinion) that ſupreme legiſlative power to Civill Magiſtrates in all matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which our Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> appropriate only to Nationall Aſſemblies: How great a ſtumbling-blocke this may grow to in time, and the miſerable conſequences thereof, I leave to your ſaddeſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoughts to be better conſidered on; and wiſh you would forbear to publiſh ſuch midnight, ſubitane, diſtracted lucubrations, as you your ſelfe well call them, to the great detriment and endangering both of Church and Common-wealth.</p>
            <div type="queries">
               <head>Twelve Queries, Eight whereof preſume to make a ſecond viſit to Mr. <hi>Pryn,</hi> importuning his reſolution in Chriſtian modeſty and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, for the ſatisfaction of many troubled conſciences.</head>
               <p n="1">1 WHether have not Parliaments and Synods of <hi>England</hi> in times paſt eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Popery? And whether may they not poſſibly do ſo again hereafter?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether in caſe a Parliament and Synod ſhould ſet up Popery, may they therein be diſobeyed by the people? If they may be diſobeyed in one particular, whether may they not upon the like grounds be diſobeyed in another? whether the people be not judge of the grounds for denying obedience to Parliament and Synod in ſuch a caſe? Whether the pretence of giving a Parliament and Synod power to eſtabliſh Religion, and yet reſerve in our own hands a Prerogative of yeelding or denying obedience thereunto, as we our ſelves thinke good, be not an
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:158481:18"/> abſolute contradiction? and laſtly, Whether they that attribute ſuch a power to Parliaments and Synods as they themſelves will queſtion and diſobey, when they thinke good, doe not in effect weaken and quite enervate the power of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or elſe condemne themſelves in cenſuring the Independents for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of obedience from Parliament and Synod in ſuch things wherein they never gave, or meant them to have power?</p>
               <p n="3">3 If the whole Kingdome may deny obedience unto Popiſh Acts and Canons, or upon any other the like juſt occaſion, and they themſelves be judge whether the occaſion be juſt or no; whether may not Independents, a part of the Kingdome only doe the like in all reſpects? or whether ought they becauſe a leſſer part of the Kingdome, to yeeld obedience to Popiſh Acts and Canons, becauſe a major part approve of and agree with a Parliament and Synod in eſtabliſhing them?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether would it not be an ungodly courſe for any people to hazard any thing at the diſpoſall of others, or to be carried by moſt voyces, which may poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, if not more then probably be decided in ſuch a manner as the yeelding obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence therunto would be burthenſome to their conſciences, if not abſolutely ſinfull?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Whether were it not an ungodly courſe for the whole Commons of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſo far differing in Religion as that they profeſſe before hand that they dare not yeeld to one another upon perill of damnation, to make choice of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Synod, with entring into Vow and Covenant to become afterwards all of that Religion whatſoever the Parliament and Synod ſhould agree on? whether it be not abſurd for men to ſay they will be of ſuch a Religion as ſhall be ſetled, before they ſee evidence to convince them? and whether it be in the power of man to be really of what Religion he will, untill he ſee reaſon &amp; demonſtration for it?</p>
               <p n="6">6 If a repreſentative State or Magiſtrate may make Laws for ſetting up a Religion, or eſtabliſhing what Church government they pleaſe; whether have not the people the ſame power originally in themſelves, to aſſume again, and put it in execution when they pleaſe? and whether were this otherwiſe then to attribute unto a mixt multitude to the World, if not abſolutely as it is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from the Saints in Scripture, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 18, 19. and 17. 6. 9. 11. 14. at leaſt by moſt voices, to make choice of a Religion, Laws and Diſcipline, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Saints, houſhold, and Church of God muſt neceſſarily be governed?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Suppoſe a Luther an and Calviniſt, or any others differing in opinion; whether they may out of hypocriſie or implicitly ſubmit and be conformable to one anothers diſcipline and doctrine whereof they doubt, before they be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced? Whether have either of them an infallible way to convince the other, and bring them over to be ſincerely of their opinion before their underſtandings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied? if they have, why doe they not put it in execution? if they have not, why ſhould they be offended with one another if they continue differing?</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:158481:19"/> 8 Whether oppoſing Gods people or their wayes be not a fighting againſt God? whether it be not extreameſt raſhneſſe, if not abſolute madneſſe and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption to attempt any thing which may poſſibly prove a fighting againſt God? and whether any man in theſe dayes can have a fuller aſſurance in his owne conſcience, or give better evidence unto others that he doth not oppoſe the people of God whileſt he oppoſes ſuch as differ from him in opinion, than <hi>Paul</hi> whileſt he <hi>perſecuted the Church,</hi> Phil. 3 6. <hi>thought he ought to do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things contrary to the Name of Jeſus of Nazareth,</hi> Act. 26. 9?</p>
               <p n="9">9 Which of the two parties may beſt be thought proud, preſumptuous or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious? whether Independents who ſeeke only to enjoy their owne conſciences in all peaceableneſſe and meekneſſe, without giving the leaſt diſturbance to ſuch as differ from them in opinion; or the Preſbyterians, who <hi>Haman</hi> like, are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver at reſt within themſelves, untill they bring all others to be conformable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them both for Diſcipline and Doctrine, though to an equall judge they may probably, be as erronious as other mens; and poſſibly, moſt ſuperſtitious and hereticall?</p>
               <p n="10">10 If there be but one Chriſt and many Antichriſts; one true way and many falſe: Whether doe not all men and women in generall, and every one in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, run a greater hazard to have the truth with-held from them both in Diſcipline and Doctrine, if all manner of opinions and religious worſhip but one, were baniſhed the Country where they live, than if there were a toleration of them all?</p>
               <p n="11">11 If a State may lawfully compell a Nation to be of this or that Religion, as in <hi>Spaine, Italy,</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> during the Biſhops Reigne; Whether is it poſſible for the people of ſuch a Nation to be damned by ſubmitting to ſuch State Religions, though falſe? Whether are not ſuch reſpective States bound in juſtice to be accountable for all the ſoules which doe miſcarry by conforming unto ſuch State Religions? And whether were it diſcretion for any man to runne a hazard of ſo many ſoules, though he might thereby gaine the Empire of the World?</p>
               <p n="12">12 Whether are not all Religions alike, nothing available to ſalvation, to him that takes his Religion upon truſt? If we be obliged to try the Spirits, to ſearch the Scriptures, and hold faſt the truth, whether muſt we not be fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded thereof in our ſelves, according to our owne reaſon and underſtanding? Whether is there a neceſſity that the State Religion for the time in faſhion, muſt alwayes appeare to be the true one, in every mans judgement, who really endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and deſires to have ſuch an opinion of it, ſo it might be with a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? And what Goſpell warrant is there for Magiſtrates impriſoning, fining, baniſhing, or ſo much as diſcountenancing any man for not beleeving, or not doing that, which he could not poſſibly beleeve, or doe without ſinning damnably?</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
